It's happened to all of us: a song comes on the radio, and we are immediately transported to a time in our past.
我们都有过这样的经历：收音机里播放一首歌，我们立刻被带回到过去的某个时刻。
But what is it that makes music so effective at doing this?
但究竟是什么能让音乐如此有效地做到这一点呢？
There are a few things that link tunes with our memories.
有几种因素将曲调与我们的记忆联系起来。
Paul Donoghue, writing for ABC News, reminds us that the emotional nature of music helps make it particularly memorable.
为ABC新闻撰稿的保罗·多诺霍提醒我们，音乐的情感特性使其尤其令人难忘。
And Kelly Jakubowski, an assistant professor in music psychology, adds that music and singing are often part of many important life events and rituals, and that it is also very effective in grabbing our attention.
音乐心理学助理教授凯利·雅库博夫斯基补充说，音乐和歌唱常常是许多重要生活事件和仪式的一部分，并且在吸引我们的注意力这件事上它也极为有效。
These things combined mean that music and these life events are likely to be encoded together in our memories.
这些因素综合起来意味着，音乐和这些生活事件很可能在我们的记忆中被一同编码。
Music itself is easy to remember.
音乐本身就很容易被记住。
Tiffany Jenkins, writing for BBC Culture, tells us how throughout history oral cultures have passed important knowledge from generation to generation through song.
蒂芙尼·詹金斯为BBC文化撰稿时告诉我们，纵观历史，口述文化如何通过歌曲将重要知识代代相传。
The rhythm, rhyme, melody and alliteration in lyrics all serve as memory aids.
歌词的节奏、韵律、旋律和头韵都起到了辅助记忆的作用。
She goes on to say that pop music especially can be associated with a particular moment in time.
她接着说道，流行音乐尤其可以与特定的时刻相关联。
As Shahram Heshmat, writing in Psychology Today highlights, we often become familiar with a piece of music because we hear it as background music.
正如沙赫拉姆·赫什马特在《今日心理学》上所强调的，我们常常因为将一首音乐作为背景音乐聆听而对其熟悉起来。
Familiarity is important.
熟悉程度很重要。
Jakubowski, tells us that the more familiar a piece of music is, the more effective it is at bringing back memories.
雅库博夫斯基告诉我们，一首音乐越熟悉，就越能有效地唤起记忆。
This applies to music more than other cultural products because we are far more likely to hear a song over and over again than watch a film or a TV programme in the same way.
在这一点上，音乐比其他文化产品更是如此，因为我们反复听一首歌的可能性远比用同样的方式反复看一部电影或电视节目要大得多。
Heshmat points out that our musical preferences usually form during our teens, and this corresponds with what many experts call the 'reminiscence bump', where we make our strongest memories between the ages of 10 and 30.
赫什马特指出，我们的音乐偏好通常在青少年时期形成，这与许多专家所说的"回忆高峰"相吻合，即在10到30岁之间，我们形成最强烈的记忆。
It's clear that our memories and music are closely linked – to the point that music is being used to help dementia sufferers access memories that they thought they had lost.
很明显，我们的记忆和音乐紧密相连——以至于音乐正被用来帮助痴呆症患者找回他们以为已经失去的记忆。